Hello.
同学
What does the debate
辩论对于你来讲
mean to you?
意味着什么
For me
对于我来讲
it means clouds, mountains
它意味着云 意味着山
and the other end of them.
意味着云和山的彼端
Come to join
加入我们东财大
debate team two of DUFE.
辩论二队吧
Team two?
二队
I thought I have the chance to join team one.
我还以为是一队呢
Goodbye.
打扰了
Hello.
同学
Life is not only for the present
人生不止有眼前的苟且
but also the debate and dreams.
还有辩论和远方
Debate?
辩论
Aren't you from the Comic Association?
你们不是动漫社的吗
We can also talk about the comic first.
也可以先聊会儿动漫
Long distance separates no bosom friends.
海内存知己 天涯若
Stop.
你不用说了
If you take elective courses for me
你帮我代课上选修
I'll join you.
我就加入你们社团
But I'm a teacher.
我可是老师啊
Bye.
告辞
Why are you sitting here?
你坐在这里干嘛
There's nobody here, is there?
不是没人了吗
I'll accompany you here.
我陪陪你
I've got a piece of grapevine.
我带来了一个小道消息
What stocks?
什么股啊
Pack it in.
别闹
I have asked the director.
我问过主任啦
He said when Ma Nan was a freshman,
他说马楠大一的时候
he was the
原来是
wonderful fourth debater of law school.
法律系的黄金四辩
He never lost.
从来没输过
But everyone does not know why that
但是不知道为什么
in the second semester
到了大一第二个
of his freshman year,
学期的时候
he seldom went there.
就开始不怎么去了
He completely quit by his second year.
到了大二就彻底退队了
It's said that he didn't come back
听说当时学校三顾茅庐
even the school called on him repeatedly at that time.
都没能请得动他
Is he so famous?
他那么出名
How come no one knows him?
那怎么没人知道
That's normal.
正常
When Hao was a freshman
小好姐刚进大学的时候
Ma Nan was in his junior year.
人马楠都大三了
No his legend already.
早就没有江湖传言了
Hurry up, hurry up.
那赶紧赶紧
Invite him to join us
让他来我们队
as a fourth debater.
给我们当四辩
So we can defeat
这样我们就能打败
team one.
一队了
Don't you hear it?
刚没听说
He was the fourth debater who never lost.
人家是不败四辩吗
How can Nan Bei persuade him?
南北怎么可能说得过他
Hey, hey, hey.
哎哎哎
You can say I'm not good at debating.
你说我辩论不行倒行
But you can't say
你不能说我
I'm not good at fooling.
忽悠人不行啊
You, a man who likes taking shortcuts
像你这种走捷径的人设
have no idea what to do next
碰到这种硬茬
when you meet a hard man like him, right?
没辙了吧
I shall take full charge of the matter.
包我身上
What are you doing?
你们干嘛呢
Ma Nan says meditation is
马楠说冥想是
the latest method to keep healthy.
最新的保养办法
It can find a cure
可以妙手回春
and change the structure of the brain.
还可以改变大脑的结构
Then I can
这样我就可以
understand art.
看得懂艺术
Then I can keep up with
就能跟得上
what Jingwen says.
静雯的话题了
You may not pass
就你们俩现在这样
the nine-year compulsory education
别说四级了
according to your current situation
九年义务教育
not to mention CET-4.
都不一定合格
Do you know that?
你知道吗
Here you are.
给你
Oh!
哟
You are really something.
可以呀
At the very most
这些东西平时撑死
it is worth 200 yuan in normal times.
卖两百
I must try my best
给你办事
since I work for you.
那肯定得用点心啊
You can regard these
你就当这些
as the presents.
都是我孝敬你的
What do you want me to do?
想求我什么事
Well.
那
Let me be straight with u.
哥们之间就不绕弯子了
At present
现在呢
Our debate team
我们辩论队
is suffering now.
是处于水深火热的阶段
I want to invite you to return to join us
我呢 想请你出山
as the fourth debater.
给我们打四辩
Ma Nan, you have ever debated?
马楠 还打辩论呢
Look.
你看
Ma is like
小马哥这种
a deep ocean of secrets.
深不可测的人设
You wouldn't understand.
你不懂了吧
You are really something.
可以
Well done in espionage.
谍报工作做得不错
But I'm not interested in it.
可是我没兴趣
Why?
为 为什么呀
I'm in my fifth year of DUFE.
我都大五了
Graduation is a problem for me.
毕业都成问题
What does debate for?
还打什么辩论
Well, Ma Nan.
那个 马楠
Enter for CET-4
你赶紧把
right now.
英语四级报上去
Li came again today.
今天老李又登门拜访了
Yes, yes, yes.
对 对对
Well, enter for CET-4 first.
那个 你先把四级报了
Solve the matter of extreme urgency first.
先解决燃眉之急
We'll talk about
咱辩论的事
the debate later, OK?
以后再说好不好
I won't enter for the exam.
不报
No way.
那可不行
It's hard to find a job
你这要是没有毕业证
without a diploma.
出去找工作都不好找
No way.
那可不行
If you don't find a job
那找不到工作
you won't afford to buy a house.
就买不了房
No way.
那可不行
You won't marry if you don't have your own house.
你没有房你就没媳妇儿
Will you have it all after graduation?
毕业了就有这些吗
In my opinion
要我说
you're too naive.
你们还是太年轻了
Let me just give you an example.
给你们举个例子
What will happen after graduation?
毕业了能怎么样
Earn a few thousand of yuan a month.
一个月几千块钱
Not enough for your expense.
不够花
You have to ask your parents for money.
你还得回头向你父母要
And you will face
还有四面八方
the expectations
而来的那种
from everywhere.
望你成龙的想法
It's worse
那比现在是有过之
than it is now.
而无不及呀
You don't know it till you try it.
那你不试试怎么知道
With my understanding of
以哥们对你这
your ability of fooling,
忽悠的能力的理解
I think you must be able to
我觉得你以后在
make a difference
职场里面
in the workplace.
绝对会杀出一片天地来
Yes.
是
You don't know it till you try it.
不试不知道
You'll try it sooner or later.
早晚要一试的呀
What's the hurry?
急什么
I can stay until my seventh year.
能待到大七
In my seventh year
大七啊
I can graduate as long as I want to.
想毕业怎么都能毕业
You just seize the day to enjoy
你们赶紧就
the scenery around you
看看周围的风景
and chase after the girls around you.
把把附近的妹子
Do you three have girlfriends?
你们仨有女朋友吗
Not
还
yet.
没有
Look.
还是啊
What are you thinking about?
想什么呢
Sleep.
睡觉
Can I ask for
那我那四级
a refund of the fee for CET-4?
报名费还能退吗
I am worthless.
我啥也不是
Why do you get me here
深更半夜的
since there is only you
孤男寡女的
at this late hour?
你把我叫这儿来干嘛
You think too much.
大哥你想多了好不好
I'm here because these two books
因为这两本书
cannot be taken out at all.
根本不外借
I can't even get it during the day.
白天也抢不着
Don't make excuses.
你别找理由啊
Why me?
那为什么偏偏是我呢
Nonsense.
你不废话吗
Who else can I get except you?
不是你 是谁呀
You're barely
咱队里
the only man on our team.
勉强就你一个男的
In case something happens,
那万一出点什么事
you can protect me.
你不得保护我呀
Don't worry.
你放心
I can definitely run faster than you
万一出什么事
if something happens.
人家跑得绝对比你快
Think about yourself.
你说你一天天
Have you figured out
你说服马楠的事
how to persuade Ma Nan?
你整明白了吗
No entering for CET-4.
不考四级
No joining us as the fourth debater.
不打四辩
He doesn't want to do anything
啥也不干
I don't know what he wants.
不知道想干嘛
What did he get on CET-4?
他以前四级考多少分
Director Li said that
李主任说
he never entered for CET-4.
他压根就没考过
Is he afraid of
他是不是因为怕考了
failing the exam
四级考不过
and not getting his diploma?
然后拿不了毕业证
So it leaves a psychological shadow?
有心理阴影啊
He is afraid of graduating successfully
他就是怕考了四级
with passing CET-4
有了毕业证
and getting his diploma.
他就怕毕业
Not really.
不至于吧
Granted, our school is good,
咱们学校是挺好的
but there's no way he doesn't want to leave.
但也不至于不想走啊
It is not a permanent solution.
这也不是长久之计
We really have to
真得好好给这哥们
change the guy.
改造改造了
But this guy has too many problems.
但这哥们问题太多了
I've no idea
我真不知道
where to begin.
在哪儿下手啊
Then find out
那你就先搞清楚
what happened to him first
他到底出了什么事
and the reason why he degenerate like this.
为什么堕落成现在这样
Then suit your methods to the situation.
然后再对症下药
You have a point.
有道理啊
I'll try next time.
我下回试试
Hurry up, hurry up, hurry up.
快快快
Hurry up.
快
Sorry, sorry, sorry.
对不起 对不起 对不起
What are you doing?
干什么你
What's wrong with you?
干什么
You.
你
What did you do just now?
干什么你刚才
What are you doing?
你干嘛
Do you have a thing
你是不是对我动了
for me?
歪脑筋
What? I haven't touched you.
干什么 没有碰到你
Do you have a thing for me?
动了歪脑筋
Stop.
你别动手
You are pointing at me.
你指我
Keep your hands off me.
别动手动脚的
Don't pointing at me.
你再指我
-What?  -What are you doing?
什么动手动脚 干嘛
How dare you.
你再动
What are you doing, Qing?
小晴你干嘛呢
Didn't you agree to watch TV series together?
不是说好一起追剧吗
Why are you studying here?
你怎么在这儿学习啊
I'm done.
我完了
What's wrong?
怎么了
I'm afraid I can't pass CET-4.
四级要扑街了
CET-4 is easier than college entrance examination.
四级比高考都简单
What are you frightened of?
怕什么
I'm serious.
真的
I just finished a real test paper.
我刚做了一套真题
After a year of
我们经过
college experience,
一年大学的历练
my English is
英语水平已经低到了
so poor.
令人发指的程度
Really?
真的
How about you, Fanfan?
那凡凡呢
Have you finished any real test paper?
她做真题了吗
Yes.
做了
Just scraped a pass.
刚及格
Even you just scraped a pass,
你都刚及格
not to mention me.
那 那我更别提了
She finished the real test paper for CET-6.
她做的是六级真题
Come on.
你们加油
What a dagger in the heart!
扎心了
How about not taking the exam this time?
要不然这次还是算了吧
I won't go.
我不去
Don't be so pessimistic.
别那么悲观嘛
There is always a way to pass the exam.
考试总是有方法过的
Ma Nan
马楠
Is there
你这次
any plan for CET-4 this time?
英语四级什么安排
Comic Market.
同人祭
What? Comic Market?
同 同人祭
Do you have tickets?
有票吗
Three. Go or not?
三张 去不去
Stop being entangled with each other.
你俩别纠结了
The reputation of our school
咱这学校的九八五
will be ruined by you two sooner or later.
迟早被你俩祸祸掉
Bah!
呸
Can it be our turn
有你在
since you are here?
还能轮到我俩
Then you can
那你俩就在这儿
review here.
好好复习
I'll go out for a walk.
我出去散散步
Tao Hao
陶好
What's up?
你有什么事吗
Ma Nan
学长
Is this you?
这个是你吗
Director Li said
我听李主任说了
you were a big shot of school
听说你大一的时候
in your freshman year.
是学校的风云人物
You were not only good at debating,
不止辩论打得好
but you were also the president of the student union
还是学生会的会长
and the house captain of three associations.
三个社团的社长
You also got the national scholarship.
还拿了国家奖学金
Everyone had high hopes for you.
大家都对你寄予厚望
But nobody knew the reason.
但不知道为什么
In the end of your freshman year
到了大一结束的时候
you gave them all up.
你辞掉了所有的头衔
And you quit from the debate team.
也退出了辩论队
You even deleted all the pictures
甚至还删掉了朋友圈里
in your WeChat Moments.
所有的图片
Then
然后
you truanted frequently,
你开始频繁地翘课
failed the exam
挂科
and stayed down.
甚至留级
What do you want to say?
你想说什么
Why did you suddenly
你为什么
become so negative?
突然变得那么消极了呢
Am I negative?
消极吗
I don't think so.
我不觉得消极啊
I just chose
我只不过选了一个
a different way of
和以往不同的
being than before.
存在方式罢了
You have no any other interests
除了睡觉和打游戏
except sleeping and playing games.
你没有任何的兴趣爱好
And you didn't make friends,
也不交朋友
go to class,
课也不上
or prepare well for the exam.
考试也不好好考
And you stayed down.
还留级
You may not get your diploma.
毕业证都有可能拿不到
Is it
这就是
the way of being that you chose?
你选择的生存方式吗
Any problems?
有什么问题吗
Don't you think
你不觉得
it's a waste of your life?
这是在浪费人生吗
What's the meaning
这样的生存
of living like this?
有什么意义啊
Meaning?
意义
What do you
那你觉得
think about the meaning?
什么是意义啊
Flowers and applause?
鲜花掌声
Come out in front?
名列前茅
Or find
还是毕业以后
a good job after graduation?
找个体面的工作
We will be in a suit
西装革履的
and get well paid.
收入也不菲
Or feasting
还是灯红酒绿
and revelry?
觥筹交错
Don't you think
你不觉得这一切
it's like being put on
就像是被放在一个
a treadmill that
永远停不了的
can never stop?
跑步机上吗
You can only run forward involuntarily,
你只能身不由己地
mechanically,
机械地
and desperately.
拼命地往前跑
When a person is raised
当一个人被泡沫
by bubbles,
浮得越高的时候
in order to prevent it from bursting,
为了防止它爆裂
you have to run higher
你就得一遍一遍地
again and again
往更高的地方跑
and so on.
如此循环
Do you think
你觉得
it's the meaning of life?
这就是人生的意义吗
I remember one summer vacation.
我记得以前有一年暑假
A friend of mine
我有一个朋友
died in a drowning accident while swimming.
游泳溺水了
He often goes to the lake.
他经常去那个湖里玩
No one
没有人比他
knows the lake better than him.
更清楚那片湖
How absurd!
荒谬吧
We are
我们明明
so small and ignorant.
那么渺小和无知
However, we're always of self-righteousness
却还总是自以为是的
standing on the commanding heights
站在制高点上
and measuring each other's value
用各自的标尺
with our own standards
去衡量彼此的价值
and calling it the meaning in the end.
将之称为意义
I'm tired of
我早就厌倦了
coming again and again.
这样的轮回了
When you start to
当你开始追求
pursue the meaning,
意义的时候
you've long
你早就被
been trapped by it.
意义牢牢地套死了
You've long been chained to
你早就被拴在那个
the treadmill that can never stop.
一直跑动的跑步机上
The only way to stop all this
唯一停止这一切的方法
is to stop pursuing meaning.
就是不再追求意义
So
所以
you.
你
I chose to get off
我选择从跑步机上
the treadmill.
走下来
Oh my god.
哎呀
It's too early.
这才几点呀
What can we do?
有什么办法呢
Team one has told us
咱们教室
about the classroom.
人家一队跟你说了
If you want to
如果你们想用
use the classroom,
这个教室呢
you can use it before eight in the morning,
就必须在早上八点之前
in the lunch hour
中午十二点
from 12 to 13,
到一点的午休时间
and after 12 p.m.
以及晚上十二点之后
God. Why is it so dark?
天呐 怎么这么黑呀
You're here.
你们来了
Ah!
哎呀
Hao, why are you here?
小好姐 你怎么在这儿
What are you doing here?
你在这儿干嘛呢
I studied all the competitions before the league
我研究了一队统计的
according to the statistics of team one.
联赛前的所有比赛
Finally, I found a
终于让我找到了一个
Qiuyi Cup Debate Competition.
秋奕杯辩论大赛
Qiuyi Cup?
秋奕杯
It sounds fake.
听着怪山寨的
Yes.
对
It's not as good as the Coal Cup
还没有我们上周打的
we took part in last week.
煤炭杯的级别高呢
But
但是
the school of finance also attended the competition.
金融学院的也参加了
Really?
真的假的
Who?
谁呀
The top four of the provincial competition last year.
去年省大赛四强
Top four?
四强
How could they
他们怎么会
take part in such a competition?
参加这种比赛
I don't know.
不知道
Perhaps it was the result of a moment's inattention.
可能是手滑了吧
But it's not important.
但不重要
As long as we can defeat them...
只要我们能够战胜他
We can become famous.
就能一战成名
Then we won't have to
再也不用看
care about team one anymore.
一队的脸色了
But they are top four.
但是人家是四强啊
How can we defeat them?
我们怎么能赢啊
I think it shouldn't be an issue
我觉得问题不大
as long as we can
只要我们能够
persuade Ma Nan.
搞定马楠
That's all?
就这样
Yes, that's all.
对 就这样
So
所以呀
no Hisashi Mitsui's great change
没有你们想象的
as you think.
三井寿的巨变
No family accidents.
也没有家庭变故
He
他呀
has developed a habit of degenerating.
就是堕落成习惯了
It's terrible for a person
一个人要是懒散起来
to be lazy.
也是太可怕了
Ma Nan said
马楠说
he didn't think he was degenerate.
他也没觉得自己是堕落
He just felt that compared with the previous life
就是觉得比起之前那种
of seizing every minute,
只争朝夕的生活
sleeping late and playing games
睡睡懒觉 打打游戏
are more comfortable.
来得更舒服一点
He always felt that he had a good foundation.
总觉得自己基础好
He could catch up with others
等想补的时候
if he wanted.
总能补上来的
He didn't expect that
没想到
in his senior year,
等到了大四的时候
the classmates around him
身边的同学
were starting preparing
都已经开始准备
for their papers
毕业论文
and finding jobs
找工作的时候
He had
他呀
developed a habit of being lazy.
已经懒散成习惯了
He also had the idea
他也曾有过一丝丝
of trying to cheer up.
想要打起精神的念头
But
可是马上
he was defeated by inertia immediately.
又被惯性打败了
When he finally thought
等他终于
he had ushered in the ultimate trial
以为自己迎来了
of not being able to graduate，
无法毕业的终极审判时
guess what.
你们猜怎么着
His graduation can be delayed.
这样竟然还能延毕
Such a life
这样的生活
can continue.
竟然还能够继续
Bingo!
答对了
Actually, it's normal.
其实也很正常
He doesn't even care about graduation，
人连毕业都不当回事
not to mention come here
更何况来咱们这儿
to debate.
打辩论了
Don't bet on it.
那可不一定啊
After all, he had
人家毕竟是对生活
a glimmer of hope for life.
有过一丝丝希望的人
Such a person is not too difficult to save.
这样的人不算太难救
After all
毕竟
nobody wants to
没有人想
born a good-for-nothing.
天生就当废物
So if we can
所以如果我们
help him
能够帮他
cheer him up and face the graduation，
打起精神面对毕业
then there is the possibility
那他说不定
that he can walk it back.
就能回到以前的状态
Then our problem
那我们的问题
might be solved.
没准也能迎刃而解
We're friends.
兄弟一场
I'll have a try.
我试试
That's it. It's like our life.
没办法 人生写照
Still at the starting point.
不还是起点吗
How about this?
这样
Gamble big.
咱玩一大的
If I win
我要赢了呢
you enter for CET-4.
你去报四级
If you win
你要赢了呢
take part in our debate team.
你就来我们队打辩论
Lead us to a victory
打四辩带领我们
as the fourth debater, OK?
走向胜利好不好
No way.
没门
There are only two options anyway.
反正就AB俩选项
Choose one.
选一个
I choose C.
我选C
I usually choose C for questions that I can't do.
一般不会的题我都选C
What's wrong with you?
怎么回事啊
You have a typical
你这典型的
graduation phobia, you know?
毕业恐惧症知道吗
You're so weak.
能不能行了
So annoying.
我说你烦不烦
Are you particularly idle lately?
你最近是不是特别闲啊
Do you have a girlfriend?
有女朋友吗
Can you defeat Liu Yanze in the debate?
你辩论打得过刘彦泽吗
Have you entered for CET-4?
你四级报了吗
We met by chance.
大家萍水相逢的
Leave me alone.
早点洗洗睡了啊
What? I take you as a brother, but you...
不 我拿你当兄弟 你却
We both sleep in the same room.
咱俩都睡一屋了
Why did you say we met by chance?
还萍水相逢
I'm not playing anymore, bye.
不玩了 走了
You win?
赢了
The points?
几点
Six.
六点
Boring.
没劲
Let's turn to
我们先翻到
page 102 first.
课本的一百零二页
Let's look at some problems
我们先看一下上周
in an article we learned
学过一篇文章的
last week.
一些问题
Look at the first question.
先看一下第一个问题
The first question is
第一个问题是
why does William say
为什么威廉觉得
that nationality
他是哪国人
makes no difference for him?
对他来说不重要
Anybody knows?
有谁知道吗
Where is it?
哪儿呢
Do you understand what she said?
这能听懂吗
Nonsense.
废话
Let me tell you.
跟你说 你有这时间呐
Hurry back to the dormitory to
赶紧回宿舍
review your CET-4 if you have time.
复习你的四级去吧
Why are you here every day
你天天你跟我在这儿
and auditing in my class?
蹭我们班课算怎么回事
Didn't he accompany you to class?
不是陪你上课嘛
What else?
问啥呀
I'm at odds with Ma Nan.
我跟马楠闹别扭了
So I come out.
出来躲躲
You didn't succeed?
没成功
The best debater is not unworthy of the title.
你当他最佳辩手白拿的
Listen.
你听我说啊
He may not have no desire
他可能真的不是
to cheer up.
不想振作起来
It's just that his current state
只不过他现在的状态
shows that he has no ability to change it.
说明他有点超纲了
If it doesn't matter by strategy,
你呀 智取不行
then get tough.
就来硬的
Look at what he is
他平时
in normal times.
贱兮兮那样子
It's not impossible.
也不是不行
I'll have a try.
试试吧
Does anyone know the answer?
有同学知道答案的吗
The boy in yellow.
那个黄衣服的同学吧
Yes, it's you.
对 就是你
I choose C.
我选C
Boy, it's an essay question.
同学 这个是问答题
I choose C for questions that I can't do.
我就选C
Forget it. Sit down.
算了 你坐下吧
It's training time for team one now.
现在是一队的训练时间
I'm not here to be trained.
我不是来训练的
I come to talk to you.
我是来找你的
These are
这是我
butter cookies made by myself.
自己做的黄油曲奇
I misunderstood
之前是我误会了
you and Qiu Lingyan before.
你和秋凌烟学姐
And I said many harsh words.
还说了很多过分的话
Don't mind please.
希望你别在意
That's nothing.
那没什么
I went too far before.
之前我也有过分的地方
After all, no one will appear in front of me
毕竟不会每天都有人
singing and dancing
载歌载舞地
every day.
出现在我面前
I quite understand.
我理解 我理解
Xiaoyu often says
小鱼她就经常说
I'm a drama queen.
我这个人比较容易戏多
So after accepting my cookies
所以这饼干你看我们就
we're even.
就当一顿泯恩仇了
Thank you, but no.
不必了
I don't eat snacks.
我不吃零食的
Are you still angry with me?
你还在生我气啊
Put it on the table.
放桌子上吧
You're eating cookies?
你在吃饼干
You never eat sweet food
我印象里
in my impression.
你从来不吃甜食啊
It might be theirs.
这可能是他们的
I was hungry.
我就是饿了
So I tasted one.
拿来尝了一块
Who bought it?
谁买的
It's delicious.
很好吃啊
Really?
有吗
Just ordinary cookies.
这不就是普通的曲奇吗
Of course you don't understand
你这种男生
sweet food.
肯定不懂甜食了
By the way,
对了
have you got the opponent's information
下一场比赛的对手资料
for the next competition?
拿到了吗
Of course.
全齐
Didn't you go to help the girl for jumble sales?
你不是去帮学妹义卖吗
Why are you here
你这在这儿
playing with buttons?
倒腾纽扣干嘛呀
For sale.
卖啊
How much are these?
这纽扣能卖多少钱
Wholesale price is 25 cents each.
批发两毛五一个
Selling price is 50 yuan each.
卖五十
Do you think
你当大家
everyone went to college
考大学都是抽签
by drawing lots?
考上来的呀
You don't understand.
这你就不懂了吧
Have you ever watched Japanese dramas?
日剧看没看过
The second button
上衣从上往下数
on the T-shirt
第二颗纽扣的位置
is closest to the heart.
最靠近心脏
If you send it to a girl,
把它送给一个女生
it means you send
就相当于
your heart to her.
把你的心送给了她
Unexpectedly,
居然
there is the girl who
有女生花
pays 50 yuan for your heart.
五十块钱买你的心
Then she should have her brain checked.
那她应该去看看脑子
You wouldn't believe me.
还不信
What are you thinking about?
想什么呢
I'm thinking
我在纠结
whether I should
到底要不要
enter for CET-4 for Ma Nan.
帮马楠报一下名
But I'm afraid he'll fall out over this.
但我又怕他翻脸
What are you afraid of?
怕什么呀
I think maybe Ma Nan
我觉得没准
also wants to enter for it.
其实马楠也想报名
It is because
就是因为
we advised too much,
我们劝得太厉害了
so it aroused
所以激发他
his dissatisfaction.
内心的小情绪
If you think so,
那你要是这么认可
you can enter for CET-4 for him.
你帮他报了吧
I have to sell buttons.
我还得卖纽扣呢
I'm leaving.
先走了啊
What are you doing?
干嘛呢
If I say
我说我
I'm finding your
在找你身上
second button,
第二个纽扣
will you believe me?
你信吗
I will.
我信
50 yuan.
五十块钱嘛
Well.
我那个
I don't want to make up stories.
我不编了
We'll talk about the fourth debater later.
四辩的事儿以后再说
But you must enter for CET-4.
但是四级你必须考
As your friend
作为兄弟
I can't see you
我不能
be so decadent.
看你这么颓废下去
If you go on like this,
你再这样下去你就废了
your life will be over.
你知道吗
Let me ask you a question.
我问你个问题
Do I have the right
我有没有
to be a good-for-nothing?
一个做废物的权利
You're thinking about
你们整天想着
competing with team one.
跟一队比赛
No problem.
没问题
That's fine with me.
我没有意见
But I tell you.
但我告诉你
I have lived such a life.
这些生活我以前过过
And mine is
而且过得
much better than yours.
比你们精彩多了
Now I only want to
我现在就想
waste my time
在这儿混吃等死
here.
过日子
Why do you have so many different opinions?
你们哪儿那么多意见
I...
我
And
还有
if you'll compete with team one
你们要跟一队比赛
I'll tell you.
我劝你
It's useless.
没用的
Throw an egg against a rock.
以卵击石
I advise you
我劝你啊
to recognize the reality.
认清现实
Don't make unnecessary struggle.
不要再做无谓的挣扎
OK?
你听不听
Ma Nan
马 马楠
Are you
你
angry with me?
不会生气了吧
It won't pay.
我犯得着吗我
The topic for the next game
下一场比赛
came out.
的辩题出来了
Should the young
年轻人是否应该
jump out of the comfort zone?
跳出舒适圈
This is an old topic.
这也算是个老辩题了吧
Comfort zone.
舒适圈
This word is so popular these two years.
这个词这两年好流行啊
Comfort zone means a person
舒适圈指的就是一个人
stays in
长期待在
a familiar environment and come into contact
熟悉的环境里面
with familiar people and things for a long time.
接触熟悉的人和事
Then he refuses to challenge anything new.
拒绝一切的挑战和可能
He lives a comfortable life.
生活安逸
Thus it forms
从而形成了
an invisible circle.
一个无形的圈子
Not that complicated.
也没有那么复杂吧
It's an environment
就是一个让
that makes you feel comfortable.
自己很舒服的环境啊
The key is that you can handle it.
关键是自己可以掌握
However
然而这种
the comfortable sensation of self-consolation
自我安慰的舒适感
and the inertia
和人的惰性
will make it easy to reject
会很容易让我们
many possibilities of change.
拒绝很多改变的可能
If you step out of the comfort zone,
但凡踏出这个舒适圈啊
then you will face
就会面对
many challenges and choices.
各种挑战和选择
You will flinch.
往往也会望而却步
Naturally
自然而然地
you'll
也就会
return back to your comfort zone.
退回自己的舒适圈
Refuse to step out and make progress.
拒绝踏出和进步
It's a cosy nest.
那不就是安乐窝吗
So what?
安乐窝怎么了
Is there any problems with a cosy nest?
安乐窝有问题吗
No problem.
没问题
But I don't think it's a commendatory term.
但总觉得不是个褒义词
I agree.
我觉得是
If we stay alone in a cosy nest
如果一直在
all the way
安乐窝里面圈地自萌
Then self-challenge and development
那自我的挑战和发展
will remain stagnant.
也就会停滞不前
Then there are
于是害怕
more and more
应对的困难和挑战
difficulties and challenges we don't want to face.
就会越来越多
The comfort zone
那舒适圈
will become smaller and smaller.
不就越来越小了
Right?
对吧
On the flip side
反过来说
if he jumps out of the comfort zone
如果他跳出舒适圈
he can be used to live in a discomfort environment
习惯了不舒适
then it will make himself comfortable again.
那会重新让自己舒适
Then the comfort zone
那这个舒适圈
will become larger and larger.
又会变得更大
It's a cycle.
这还是个循环呐
Did you notice
你们有没有发现有
there is someone like this?
一个人很像
Ma Nan
马楠
It can't be more typical.
简直不能太典型
He is now slowly
他现在是慢慢地
sinking into his comfort zone
一步一步地陷在
step by step.
自己的舒适圈里面
It's getting to be a habit with him.
无法自拔
And he keeps brainwashing
而且不断地给自己洗脑
to make himself believe
让自己相信
that he is right.
自己就是对的
It's just
只不过是
the excuse.
给自己逃避找理由罢了
to escape.
那如果
If we help him solve the problem
我们帮他解决问题呢
there is the possibility
说不定他会
that he can join us.
加入我们辩论队帮忙啊
That makes sense.
有道理啊
Who's the right person to go?
那谁去合适
I'll have a try.
那我试试吧
For the sake that you
看在你上次在礼堂
gave me a break in the auditorium last time
放我一马的份儿上
I'll give you the time before I a bowl of noodles.
我给你一碗面的时间
Please.
说吧
Ma Nan
马楠学长
I'm coming to talk about
我是想来跟您说一下
joining our debate team.
关于加入辩论队的事
Sorry.
不好意思 接个电话
Hao
小好
Hello, director Li. What's wrong?
喂 李主任 怎么了
Where did you put my papers yesterday?
我昨天的文件放哪了
Papers?
文件
I put the papers on the second shelf
文件我放在
of the first bookcase.
第一个书柜第二层了
OK, I see it.
哦 我看到了
That's good.
那就好
If you have anything to do, please contact me.
您有什么事再跟我联系
OK. Thank you.
好嘞 谢谢啊
Ma Nan, actually there are many advantages
学长 其实加入辩论队
to join the debate team.
有很多好处
Sorry.
不好意思
Hello, Weiwei. What's wrong?
喂 薇薇 怎么了
Tao Hao
陶好姐
Why are you crying?
怎么哭了
He...
他
Calm down.
你冷静点
Speak slowly.
你慢慢跟我说
He unfriended me.
他把我删了
Unfriend you? Why?
他把你删了 为什么呀
I logged off
我把他游戏账号
his game account.
给注销了
It is not an option.
那这也不是办法
You two have to communicate well.
两个人得好好沟通
Or...
那要不
I send a message to him
我给他发个信息
and ask him to friend you back, OK?
让他把你加回来好吗
That's the only way.
也只能这样了
Don't cry. Wait for my news.
先别哭了啊 等我消息
Thank you.
谢谢陶好姐
OK.
好
Hello.
喂
Hao
小好
Do you remember
课上老师说
the teacher said we should hand in
下周交幻灯片演示文件
PPT next week?
你还有印象对吧
Yes.
记得
It's about the case analysis
是关于国外收购案的
of oversea purchase.
案例分析
There are too many reference books.
参考书太多了
Do you have any?
你那儿有吗
Yes.
有
I looked it up in the library.
我查了一下那个图书馆
It is available in the library.
图书馆有的
It's about ten o'clock anyway
我这工会活动结束
when the union activity is over.
怎么着也得十点了
Then the library
那图书馆
almost has to close.
差不多也得关门了吧
I'm going there later.
我正好一会儿要去
I'll borrow it.
我去借
We will hand in PPT next Monday, right?
下周一就要交对吧
When I traveled with my roommate
我和室友周边游
it's you who bought the round-trip tickets, right?
来回车票是你买的吧
For what time?
什么时候来着
Leave the day after tomorrow and come back on Sunday night.
后天走 周日晚上回
It seems that I will miss it.
那看样子是来不及呀
Then I won't go to travel.
那旅游我就不去了吧
You can go to travel.
去呀 去呀
It's OK. I'll
没事 幻灯片演示文件
finish your PPT.
我帮你做就行
Sorry to trouble you.
那麻烦你了
Love you.
么么哒
You're welcome.
不要跟我客气了
You've finished.
吃完了
The market price of PPT
幻灯片演示文件行价
is 500 yuan each.
一份五百
Remember to collect money
下次有人再找你做
next time.
记得收钱
Sir, she pays for the bill.
老板 她买单啊
Write an invoice for me.
帮我开下发票
What are you doing?
干嘛
Are you at your period?
每个月都有那几天
I've been thinking all day.
我想了一天
I want to give up
让马楠做四辩
inviting Ma Nan to be the fourth debater.
那事我都想放弃了
You've gone over to the enemy so soon.
你这么快投靠敌方了
Think about it.
你想啊
According to his opinion
按照他的角度
even it's wrong
就算他已经废了
that he has become a good-for-nothing
一天浑浑噩噩
pissed away his time
一事无成
and achieved nothing
这些都是错的
but
但是
does he have the right
人家有没有权利
to be a good-for-nothing?
选择做一个废物
No.
没有
Why?
为什么没有
No for nothing.
就是没有
How much did our country spend on
国家从小培养他
training him from childhood?
花多少钱
How much energy did his parents spend on
父母从小养育他
him from childhood?
费多少神
How much energy did his teachers spend on
老师从小教育他
teaching him from childhood?
那得死多少脑细胞啊
Now he
现在为了
makes an excuse for himself
给自己找一借口
to be a good-for-nothing.
趴窝孵蛋
Didn't he let them down?
对得起谁呀他
What are you laughing at?
笑什么
Am I not cruel enough?
被我虐得不够狠
Listen.
你听我说
What does Ma Nan's
像马楠这种
pessimistic theoretical system with no ambition
又丧又佛的理论体系
fear most?
最害怕的是什么
He fears to meet
最害怕的就是
a stubborn female deity
遇到你这种
with high moral standards
三观极正
like you.
又一根筋的圣母
Well, the system.
那个体系
I think you are qualified for it.
你可以
You can do it.
你行 你上吧
Well.
那
I will work hard
为了我们队
for our team.
我一定努力
Show them how good you are.
关闸放鱼
Ma Nan
学长
Good morning.
早上好
You are here to
你是来给南北
bring the breakfast to Nan Bei?
送早餐的吧
No.
不是
I brought it to you on purpose
我是特意给你送的
Me?
给我
Thank you. Bye.
那谢谢啊 那我先撤了
Ma Nan
学长
Let's talk for a minute.
唠会儿呗
Are you also here to persuade me
你也是来
to join the debate team?
劝我加入辩论队的吧
Yes.
是啊
You come and go
你看你每天这
alone every day.
独来独往的
So unsociable.
一个人那么不合群
How lonely!
多孤独啊
Come to our debate team
你来我们辩论队
and experience the feeling
让你体验一把
of having friends.
有小伙伴的感受
Why should I get on well with others?
我为什么要合群啊
Human beings are social animals.
人 人是群居动物呀
But there can also be
可是也可以有
a maverick individual.
特立独行的存在呀
There are all kinds of people
这个世界上有
in this world.
各种各样的人
Their purpose is to
他的目的都是
obtain the right to live
获得生存的权利
and a better life.
和生存得更好
Survival of the fittest.
物竞天择 适者生存
There is no right or wrong,
没有什么对与错之分
light or dark.
也没有什么光明与黑暗
Survival is good
生存就是好的
and worthy of respect.
就是值得被尊敬的
Everyone is
这个世界上
a part of
每一个人都
the world.
构建了这个花花世界
Such a world will be better.
这样的世界才会更美好
Each of us lives here.
我们每个人都生存于此
Strive for
为了我们自己的
our own goals.
目标而努力
Do you understand?
你听明白了吗
It's horrible.
马楠学长太可怕了
I'm beginning to wonder
我现在开始怀疑自己了
if I should join
我到底应不应该
the debate team.
加入辩论队
Yes.
是啊
Every time I talk to him
每次跟他聊天
I have an impulse
我都有种想躺着
to lie down and do nothing.
什么都不干的冲动
The brainwashing ability of Ma Nan
马楠的洗脑能力
is too strong.
太强了
Look at you now.
瞧瞧你们一个个的
Is it that exaggerated?
有那么夸张吗
It seems that
看来
it's my turn
终于轮到我
finally.
这个大神出场
Dango
团子
Decide and act before over thinking.
你想清楚啊
It is easy for Ma Nan to brainwash.
马楠可容易洗脑人了
Don't worry.
没事
I shall take full charge of the matter.
一切就交给我吧
The flower tips move because the water moves.
水动花梢动
The shadow in the water shakes because the flower shakes.
花摇水影摇
I don't know that they have no intention
不知各无意
or they go in both directions.
为复两相招
Dango
团子
Are you OK?
没事吧
Xiaoyu
鱼
What do you think?
你说
In this vast universe,
在这茫茫的宇宙中
we humans are
我们人类如同
as small as gravel.
沙砾一般渺小
We're born
生下来注定终结
destined to end.
归于虚无
Living.
活着
What's the meaning of living?
活着又意味着什么呢
Dango
团子
It can't be...
你该不会
Xiaoyu
小鱼
What do
你说我们人类
we humans mean
在这个世界上
in this world?
到底意味着什么
Does our will really exist?
我们的意志真的存在吗
Where is the end of the universe?
宇宙的终结在哪里
What is the mystery of the universe?
宇宙的奥妙又是什么
Who can tell me?
谁能告诉我
Dango
团子
What did Ma Nan say to you?
马楠跟你说了些什么
It's all in your brain, right?
都在脑子里对不对
Throw it away.
抛掉
Don't think about it.
不要去想它
Hush.
嘘
Xiaoyu
小鱼
Look at the sunshine today.
你看今天的阳光多好啊
I'm going to catch a few rays.
我要去晒晒太阳
Bye.
再见
What should we do, Hao?
咋办 小好姐
Another one got stuck.
又绕进去一个
It's so horrible.
马楠太可怕了吧
The brainwashing ability of Ma Nan
马楠的洗脑能力
is too strong.
实在是太强了
He's like a black hole.
他就像一个黑洞
Any light will be swallowed by him.
任何光线都会被他吞噬
Those who are
但凡是意志稍微
a little less determined
不坚定一点的人
will be brainwashed by him.
都会被他洗脑
Every time I talk to him,
每次跟他聊天
I'll be brought into his logic.
都会被带进他的逻辑里
Then he persuaded me
然后他再凭借
with his deep understanding
他那套理论的深刻理解
of the theory.
说服我
But we're all debaters.
可是我们都是辩手
As a debater
身为辩手
there is no way not to think about
就没有办法不去思考
the logic and reason in each other's words.
对方话里的逻辑道理
Once you reason with Ma Nan
一旦跟他讲道理
then you'll be brought into
就会被马楠带进
his thinking space.
他的思维空间里面去
Then you will
然后渐渐对他的话
understand how he feels as well.
感同身受
He's so hard to deal with.
他真是太难对付了
We can't listen to
对待马楠这种人
what he said.
不能听他说什么
Our brains should be
脑子就应该像石头一样
as hard and stubborn as stones.
又硬又顽固
We don't have enough brain capacity
我们没有那么多脑容量
to answer him.
接他的话
Are you talking about fools?
那你们这说的是笨蛋吗
No.
不是
We can't be fools.
不能是笨蛋
We must be pure
必须是纯粹的人
and simple.
单纯的人
Our will is as firm as the sun.
意志坚定如太阳
Our hearts are as hot as a volcano.
内心灼热如火山
So that it won't be
这样才不会
swallowed by Ma Nan.
被马楠所吞噬
How could there be such a person?
怎么会有这样的人
Hello.
同学们
You guys run here, too.
你们也来跑步啊
Oh.
哎呀
It's nice to be young.
年轻真好啊
Don't be shy.
不要害羞嘛
Let's have a competition.
咱们来一场竞赛吧
I'm coming to chase you.
我来追你们